<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <title>kate-lomax</title>
    <link href="https://katelomax.net/feed.xml" rel="self" />
    <link href="https://katelomax.net" />
    <updated>2018-06-01T17:14:56+01:00</updated>
    <author>
        <name>Kate</name>
    </author>
    <id>https://katelomax.net</id>

    <entry>
        <title>Shiny and new Feminist Library catalogue</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://katelomax.net/shiny-and-new-feminist-library-catalogue/"/>
        <id>https://katelomax.net/shiny-and-new-feminist-library-catalogue/</id>

        <updated>2018-06-01T17:14:15+01:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://katelomax.net/media/posts/12/" alt="" />
                <p>I recently worked with the <a href="http://www.feministlibrary.co.uk" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Feminist Library</a> to upgrade and migrate their Koha-based Library Management System. </p>
<p>We made quite a leap from version Koha 3.12 to 17.11 and the new, shiny and responsive (!) catalogue is now available at: </p>
<p><a href="https://catalogue.feministlibrary.co.uk">https://catalogue.feministlibrary.co.uk</a></p>
<p>I haven't worked with <a href="https://koha-community.org">Koha LMS</a> much recently so it's good to be back and see all the great work that's happened on one of the best and friendliest open source projects in libraryland. </p>
<p>And, digging through my notes, it looks like the first time I installed Koha for the Feminist Library was way back in  2008! </p>
<p>Looking forward to seeing their collection continue to expand and evolve. </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>Back to blogging</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://katelomax.net/switching-to-publii/"/>
        <id>https://katelomax.net/switching-to-publii/</id>

        <updated>2018-05-14T11:16:07+01:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Back to blogging, it's been a while. I've been writing in lots of other places, but now want to get back to keeping notes and sharing ideas here as well.</p>
<p>This blog has now moved from Middleman to being Publii-powered. At least for now. </p>
<p> </p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title> Announcing Making Library Makers</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://katelomax.net/announcing-making-library-makers/"/>
        <id>https://katelomax.net/announcing-making-library-makers/</id>
            <category term="making"/>
            <category term="makerspaces"/>
            <category term="libraries"/>
            <category term="learning"/>
            <category term="education"/>

        <updated>2018-04-12T13:05:46+01:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>From the launch announcement:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It's challenging thing to deliver training for makers and making online - we've approached this by focusing on providing a friendly and supportive online learning environment in which learners can tackle real projects that are relevant to the type of library they work in. And they have access to trainers to get help and ask questions at every step of the way.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If you want to find out more about Making Library Makers, check it out at <a href="http://www.makinglibrarymakers.com">www.makinglibrarymakers.com</a>.</p>
<p>And you can read the whole blog post <a href="http://artefacto.org.uk/content/announcing-making-library-makers/">over on the Artefacto website</a>.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title> Upcoming digital maker workshops &amp; talks</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://katelomax.net/upcoming-digital-maker-workshops-and-talks/"/>
        <id>https://katelomax.net/upcoming-digital-maker-workshops-and-talks/</id>
            <category term="workshops"/>
            <category term="talks"/>
            <category term="making"/>
            <category term="makerspaces"/>
            <category term="events"/>
            <category term="conferences"/>

        <updated>2018-04-12T13:03:27+01:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                    <img src="https://katelomax.net/media/posts/3/integrated-circuit.jpg" alt="" />
                <p>There are lots of great maker events happening over the summer.</p>
<p>I'm super excited to be part of the <a href="http://www.ioi.london/makerfaire/">Institute of Imagination Mini Maker Faire</a> at OxoTowerWharf on the 11 and 12th of June. I'll be there to help out with the <a href="http://makercart.org.uk">Makercart</a>, a mobile pop-up makerspace for schools and libraries with a 3d printer, digital cutter, electronics, micro-controllers and robotics.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.artefacto.org.uk">Artefacto</a> will also be hosting a Digital Making Workshop at Redbridge Library for London Technology Week, find out more on the <a href="http://www2.redbridge.gov.uk/cms/leisure_and_libraries/libraries/events__activities/london_technology_week.aspx">Redbridge Libraries website</a>.</p>
<p>And in July you can catch us at the <a href="http://cilipconference.org.uk/">CILIP conference</a> where Carlos (of the awesome Makercart project) and I will be talking about the the <a href="http://makercart.org.uk">Makercart</a>, <a href="http://www.librarymakers.net">LibraryMakers</a> and how to get a Makerspace up and running in your library.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title> My favourite info resource is my RSS reader</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://katelomax.net/my-favourite-info-resource-is-my-rss-reader/"/>
        <id>https://katelomax.net/my-favourite-info-resource-is-my-rss-reader/</id>
            <category term="writing"/>
            <category term="rss"/>
            <category term="jinfo"/>

        <updated>2018-04-12T13:05:14+01:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <div class="header-section">I <a href="https://web.jinfo.com/go/blog/73489">recently contributed</a> to the <em>My Favourite Tipples</em> series on Jinfo, listing some of my favourite online information resources. This was much harder than I thought (both limiting it to 4 items and not leaning too heavily on development tools).</div>
<div class="container">
<div class="content">
<article class="col blog-post">
<p>But it also made me aware of how much I rely on RSS and other content syndication when writing <a href="http://libraries.newslet.org/">Newslet for Libraries</a> and for generally keeping on top of different things I'm interested in. RSS is not dead but it's definitely due some TLC (and <a href="http://www.theawl.com/2016/04/o-reader-my-reader">Google Reader is gone but not forgotten</a>).</p>
<p>Syndication is still a big part of how we navigate the web but the shape of this has changed and will continue to change. Last year, <em>MakeUseOf</em> took a look at <a href="http://www.makeuseof.com/tag/rss-dead-look-numbers/">the numbers of RSS use</a> but with the growing popularity of Read Later apps, the proliferation of news syndication apps and as Facebook's walled garden <a href="http://staynalive.com/2016/04/if-you-didnt-think-rss-was-dead-before-facebook-just-killed-it-completely.html">continues to close in on us</a>, there's a need for an open standard now more than ever.</p>
<p>Anyway, you can check out the post on the <a href="https://web.jinfo.com/go/blog/73489">Jinfo Blog</a>.</p>
</article>
</div>
</div>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title> For when you need to install Omeka on shared hosting</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://katelomax.net/for-when-you-need-to-install-omeka-on-shared-hosting/"/>
        <id>https://katelomax.net/for-when-you-need-to-install-omeka-on-shared-hosting/</id>
            <category term="tips"/>
            <category term="omeka"/>
            <category term="note-to-self"/>
            <category term="management"/>
            <category term="documentation-matters"/>
            <category term="content"/>
            <category term="archiving"/>

        <updated>2018-04-12T13:07:56+01:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>It's not always possible to install <a href="http://omeka.org">Omeka</a> on a VPS or other dedicated server. Sometimes you just have to make do with shared web hosting and all of the caveats that come with that.</p>
<p>These are some collected notes about troubleshooting Omeka installation on shared hosting based on some of my own trial and error and some useful responses from the kind people on the <a href="http://omeka.org/forums/">Omeka support forums</a>.</p>
<p>The full requirements for installing Omeka available <a href="http://omeka.org/codex/Preparing_to_Install">here</a> but it's the <em>mod_rewrite</em> and <em>ImageMagick</em> ones that can be particular bugbears.</p>
<p>There are a list of <a href="http://omeka.org/codex/Hosting_Suggestions">'Hosting suggestions'</a> on the Omeka site to help spare you some of this pain but they are largely US-based and focused on academic institutions.</p>
<h3 id="enable-development-mode">Enable development mode</h3>
<p>The first step in troubleshooting is to know what the trouble is that you're .. ummm .. shooting. You can enable error reporting on Omeka by uncommenting the relevant line in the .htaccess file in your root directory</p>
<p><code>SetEnv APPLICATION_ENV development</code></p>
<h3 id="imagemagick">ImageMagick</h3>
<p>ImageMagick is required by Omeka for resizing and processing images and other file uploads. You can install Omeka but it requires shell access to the server which isn't available on a lot of shared hosting (<a href="https://www.webfaction.com/">Webfaction</a> is the only exception that springs to mind).</p>
<p>First, if you have ImageMagick installed it a) has to be the executable version and b) you need to know the location so you can add this to the admin settings. This is usually /usr/bin but not always.</p>
<p>You can check the directory path is added correctly from the Admin settings page</p>
<p><img src="http://katelomax.net/images/omeka-directory-path-screenshot.jpg" alt="ImageMagick directory path"></p>
<p>If you're on shared hosting and ImageMagick either isn't installed or otherwise isn't working, you can try using the PHP extension instead of the executable version of ImageMagick. This is via the imagick PECL package that can be installed from cPanel.</p>
<p>You'll need to update the configuration to bypass the expected ImageMagick setup.</p>
<p>In the application/config/config.ini file, uncomment the line and change it from:</p>
<p><code>fileDerivatives.strategy = "Omeka_File_Derivative_Strategy_ExternalImageMagick"</code></p>
<p>to:</p>
<p><code>fileDerivatives.strategy = "Omeka_File_Derivative_Strategy_Imagick"</code></p>
<p>This will remove the directory path option from the settings page but will allow you to upload files to items in your Omeka collection.</p>
<h3 id="too-many-redirects">Too many redirects</h3>
<p>Another issue you might encounter is that ol' 'too many redirects ' loop when trying to access the installer.</p>
<p>This can usually be resolved by ensuring there is an .htaccess file in the installation directory as well as the site's root folder:</p>
<p>Something like:</p>
<pre><code class="highlight plaintext">&lt;Files install.php&gt;
Allow from all
&lt;/Files&gt;

&lt;Files mod-rewrite.php&gt;
Allow from all
&lt;/Files&gt;

&lt;Files check-mod-rewrite.html&gt;
Allow from all
&lt;/Files&gt;

# This allows us to verify that mod_rewrite is enabled
&lt;IfModule mod_rewrite.c&gt;
RewriteEngine On

# If know that mod_rewrite is enabled, but you are still getting mod_rewrite errors,
# uncomment the line below and replace "/install/" with your install directory.
# RewriteBase /install/

RewriteRule ^check-mod-rewrite([^/]*)\.html$ mod-rewrite.php?enabled=true [L]
&lt;/IfModule&gt;
</code></pre>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title>An introduction to Making Library Makers</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://katelomax.net/an-introduction-to-making-library-makers/"/>
        <id>https://katelomax.net/an-introduction-to-making-library-makers/</id>

        <updated>2018-04-12T13:09:02+01:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p><em>First published on the <a href="http://www.artefacto.org.uk">Artefacto</a> blog.</em></p>
<h2 id="an-intro">An intro</h2>
<p><em>Making Library Makers; An Intro</em> was the first event for library makers run jointly by Artefacto and the Makercart Project. The event was created for staff in libraries who were interested in running maker events or otherwise learning more about the maker movement and makerspaces.</p>
<p>It was held at Makerversity, a co-working, membership-based makerspace located in the depths of Somerset House.</p>
<h2 id="why-library-makers">Why Library Makers?</h2>
<p>When we talk about 'making' and 'maker culture', we're referring to a widespread movement to create environments that enable and support learning and creativity with new and emerging technologies. This includes makerspaces, fab labs, hackerspaces, repair cafes and TechShops (though there are subtle differences, <a href="http://makezine.com/2013/05/22/the-difference-between-hackerspaces-makerspaces-techshops-and-fablabs/">depending on who you ask</a>).</p>
<p>A lot of the time, maker culture is described based on a set of tools and technologies but the specific technology involved is both fluid and largely beside the point. It's really about providing an active learning space - with a focus on creativity, open technology and collaboration.</p>
<p>All of the things that maker culture and makerspaces brought to the fore were things that had been a part of the library remit already.</p>
<p>Digital literacy and digital skills training has long been a part of public library services but the focus is often on 'web' literacy and specific digital skills. But with technology changing so rapidly and so constantly, how do we best support and prepare users with the right skills?</p>
<p>This is where 'making' comes in - it brings about a great opportunity to reimagine how we support digital literacy in libraries.</p>
<p>Above all else, the library is a learning space which is why they are such a good fit with makerspaces. It's about providing support for people to learn how to engage with new technologies creatively, collaboratively and critically.</p>
<h2 id="on-the-day">On the day</h2>
<p>This was very much an introductory event and though it was short, there was lots of interesting discussions for those who had either attended or provided maker workshops in their library.</p>
<p>Based on previous events run by Carlos (who's behind the Makercart project), the event included 'speed making' where participants got a chance to play with various maker tools and equipment, including a 3D Printer, Digital Cutter, LittleBits and MaKey MaKey. There was also a collection of books and magazines about the maker movement available.</p>
<p>The <a href="http://www.makercarto.org.uk">Makercart project</a> is a readymade 'makerspace' equipped to help libraries provide maker events and support without a huge amount of overheads.</p>
<p><a href="http://www.librarymakers.net">LibraryMakers</a> is a new website being developed to help library staff get the support they need in providing maker activities in their libraries.</p>
<p>The aim was to give people a chance to try out some different tech resources and ask any questions they might have, either to us or to others in the library sector who had been exploring maker type activities already.</p>
<p>Despite a strict schedule and a Mega Mystery Maze of a venue, everyone got a chance to try out the tools available, play a banana keyboard (or banana bongos), make circuits with LittleBits, 3D print something and use a digital cutter.</p>
<p>One of the things that we want to emphasis is that 'making' is a big, amorphous area - we're certainly not recommending any kind of uniform approach for libraries in different sectors and different communities. While getting a chance to try out some new tech tools that you haven't used before is part of it, so is the chance to discuss ideas, plans and stumbling blocks with others in the library world.</p>
<h2 id="what-next">What next</h2>
<p>We're planning further events, including some more in-depth training around specific hardware and electronics and other areas related to 'making'.</p>
<p>If you're interested in finding out more or attending future events, please sign up to the mailing list at:</p>
<p><a href="http://eepurl.com/bOzGkz">http://eepurl.com/bOzGkz</a></p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title> Interactive fiction frameworks &amp; constructivist learning</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://katelomax.net/interactive-fiction-frameworks-and-constructivist-learning/"/>
        <id>https://katelomax.net/interactive-fiction-frameworks-and-constructivist-learning/</id>
            <category term="twine"/>
            <category term="theories"/>
            <category term="pedagogy"/>
            <category term="learning"/>
            <category term="interactive"/>
            <category term="fiction"/>
            <category term="constructivism"/>
            <category term="IF"/>

        <updated>2018-04-12T13:10:29+01:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>One of the great things about Interactive Fiction frameworks like <a href="http://twinery.org">Twine</a> and <a href="http://undum.com/">Undum</a> is that their application extends far beyond creating linear text-based games (and the skies the limit, as even a cursory a glance at the <a href="https://twitter.com/twinethreads">TwineThreads</a> Twitter feed shows).</p>
<p>It's no secret that online learning suffers from high abandonment rates. It often still falls down when it comes to providing an interactive, learner-led and social learning experience and this is one of the reasons that MOOCs and other recent developments still haven't quite cracked the user engagement code.</p>
<p>Interactive fiction uses a "choose your own adventure" (for want of a better, less-trademarked term) structure. It's an interesting model for learning activities because it provides choices (and the possibility of a range of outcomes). And this can lead to learning pathways that reflect both the experiences and the goals of the learner.</p>
<p>Twine is an open source framework for creating text-based games. You can see a showcase of Twine-produced games via the Twine website at <a href="http://twinery.org/">twinery.org</a> but I guess the most well-know example is <a href="http://www.depressionquest.com/dqfinal.html">Depression Quest</a>.</p>
<p>Twine is a great tool for active learning and very easy to get started with. You don't necessarily need coding skills to create a Twine - though it certainly helps when it comes to adding additional interactions and other advanced features. There's a new online Twine authoring tool in beta and Twine clients for both Mac and Windows.</p>
<p>This is the <em>why</em> of Twine, I'll be looking into <em>How</em> to use Twine for creative learning in an upcoming post.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title> Notes and shiny new things from Mozfest 2014</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://katelomax.net/notes-and-shiny-new-things-from-mozfest-2014/"/>
        <id>https://katelomax.net/notes-and-shiny-new-things-from-mozfest-2014/</id>
            <category term="training"/>
            <category term="tools"/>
            <category term="p2pu"/>
            <category term="mozfest14"/>
            <category term="mozfest"/>
            <category term="learning"/>
            <category term="education"/>

        <updated>2018-04-12T13:12:05+01:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>The thing about Mozfest that stays with you after all the smoke has cleared is the sheer scale of the thing. Despite attending what felt like a respectable amount of sessions (summarised on the <a href="http://artefacto.org.uk/content/mozfest-2014-locating-the-library">artefacto blog</a>), I still didn't manage to make it to a fraction of the workshops that I wanted to. Mozfest is always an unrivaled exercise in FOMO, so you do need to find a balance of looking at the schedule and twitter feed and, y'know, <em>not</em> looking at the schedule or twitter feed.</p>
<p>This year, I got a chance to test out the <a href="http://howto.p2pu.org/">P2PU 'Course in a box'</a>, which provides a simple toolkit for creating open courses using Github, Discourse and Jekyll. This is something we're now considering for Flossie and other collaborative learning events.</p>
<p>There was also lots of talk about <a href="http://www.brck.com/">Brck</a>, which looks like it will come in handy for offroad (or offgrid) teaching.</p>
<p>I've been on a bit of a sabbatical from any kind of training and education provision for the past year (less teaching, more building) so it was great to hear about all the neat things that places like the <a href="http://resbaz.tumblr.com/">Research Bazaar</a> and <a href="http://software-carpentry.org/">Software Carpentry</a> do and it's reassuring to see that librarians are working hard to fill gaps left by formal LIS education - particularly <a href="https://github.com/mozillascience/training_for_libraries">when it comes to coding skills</a>.</p>
<p>And like last year, I was floored by all the great tools and platforms coming out of the data journalism world (many of which have potential applications for GLAM and digital humanities work). The <a href="http://socialmediadesk.tumblr.com/post/101175205111/every-tool-and-project-i-learned-about-at-mozfest">Social Media Desk</a> has an invaluable summary of the rest of this year's shiny new things.</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title> An introduction to keyframe CSS3 animations</title>
        <author>
            <name>Kate</name>
        </author>
        <link href="https://katelomax.net/an-introduction-to-keyframe-css3-animations/"/>
        <id>https://katelomax.net/an-introduction-to-keyframe-css3-animations/</id>
            <category term="keyframe"/>
            <category term="ebooks"/>
            <category term="animation"/>
            <category term="CSS3"/>
            <category term="CSS"/>

        <updated>2018-04-12T13:14:04+01:00</updated>
            <summary></summary>
        <content type="html">
            <![CDATA[
                <p>Part of the CSS3 specification that I've found myself using more and more are keyframe animations. If you haven't used them before, this is a bit of an overview to how keyframes are structured.</p>
<p>There are a couple of different aspects to the keyframe.</p>
<h4 id="keyframe-selector---rule-and-identifier">1. keyframe selector - @rule and identifier</h4>
<p>First, there's the keyframes @ rule where you specify your identifier (pick a name, ideally a semantic/descriptive one) for your animation that we will be referring to later in the code and define the animation sequence. You also need to include a list of keyframe selectors (waypoints for your animation). The keyframe list must at a minimum include rules for the start (0% or from) and end (100% or to) states.</p>
<h4 id="keyframe-declaration-block">2. keyframe declaration block</h4>
<p>These are the rule sets where you can configure the timing and duration and other behaviour of the animation.</p>
<p>The properties and sub-properties of the animation are applied to the HTML element you are animating. Some examples of sub-properties to declare include the <em>animation-name</em>, <em>animation-duration</em>, <em>animation-direction</em> and <em>animation-iteration-count</em> .</p>
<p>For more information about sub-properties, check out the <a href="https://developer.mozilla.org/en-US/docs/Web/Guide/CSS/Using_CSS_animations">mozilla documentation</a> which is, as always, aces.</p>
<p><em>nb. the examples are given without vendor prefixes, so don't forget to add those in live uses.</em></p>
<h3 id="code-example-1-pulsing-image">Code Example 1: Pulsing image</h3>
<pre><code class="highlight plaintext">@keyframes pulse {
 from { transform: none; }
 50% { transform: scale(1.4); }
 to { transform: none; }
 }
</code></pre>
<pre><code class="highlight plaintext"> #demo img {
/* expanded version of animation: pulse .5s infinite; */
   animation-name: pulse;
   animation-duration: 3s;
   animation-iteration-count: infinite;
 }
</code></pre>
<h3 id="example-2---fading-away-heading">example 2 - Fading away heading</h3>
<pre><code class="highlight plaintext">
 @keyframes fadeAway {
    0% {opacity: 0;}
    100% {opacity: 1;}
 }

</code></pre>
<pre><code class="highlight plaintext"> h3 {
   animation-name: fadeAway;
   animation-duration: 5s;
 }
</code></pre>
<p>And to go crazy with keyframes, check out http://www.cssanimate.com/</p>
            ]]>
        </content>
    </entry>
</feed>
